Guide to the John G. Brady Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John G. Brady papers
1867-1937
WA MSS S-1206
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18
(40 boxes) + 1 broadside
The collection consists of the personal and official papers of John G. Brady documenting early missionary work in Alaska, the history and political and economic development of Alaska, and Brady's life and career. There are early 20th century publications by Alaskan government bodies and missionary groups, as well as the public records of the City of Sitka. Included are photographs, negatives, and glass lantern slides of Alaskan scenery and subjects, native Alaskans, and Brady's family.
Brady, John Green, 1847-1918
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The John G. Brady Papers were given to Yale University Library in 1954-55, by the children of John G. Brady. Seventeen letters from Brady to Henry Baldwin and two letters from Mrs. Sarah Baldwin to Henry Baldwin were purchased by the Library in 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOHN GREEN BRADY (1848-1918)
John Green Brady was born June 15, 1848 in New York City. Following his mother's death, he ran away from home and was later sent to a refuge for homeless boys on Randall's Island. In 1859 the Children's Aid Society sent him to live with John Green, at that time a state legislator and later a judge, on his farm near Tipton, Indiana. Brady worked his way through Yale College, graduating with the Class of 1874, then entered Union Theological Seminary, where he was active in city missionary work. After graduating in 1877, he travelled to Texas, where he planned to open a training farm for New York slum boys. However, lack of funds forced him to abandon this project.
In March, 1878, Brady arrived in Alaska, under the auspices of the Presbyterian Board of Home Missions, to establish a mission school at Sitka. His fellow missionary, Dr. Sheldon Jackson, became a close friend and associate for many years. In 1881, Brady founded the Sitka Boys' Home, but he soon resigned his official position when the Presbyterian mission board objected to the personal profits he gained from opening a saw mill business as a trade school for boys. Yet Brady continued to serve the native Alaskans as an independent missionary, while working as manager of the Sitka Trading Company.
John G. Brady married Elizabeth Patton on October 20, 1887, in Cochranton, Pennsylvania. Their five children were John Green, Jr., Hugh Patton, Sheldon Jackson, Mary Beattie, and Elizabeth Patton.
Brady soon became interested in Alaska politics. In December, 1884, President Arthur appointed him to the Sitka Commissariat. As a United States commissioner, Brady became a vocal opponent of Governor Alfred P. Swineford, whom he considered an enemy of Alaska's missionaries. Brady and his friends campaigned unsuccessfully for his appointment as governor after Benjamin Harrison was elected president in 1888. However, in June 1897, President McKinley appointed John G. Brady to be the fifth territorial governor of Alaska.
In his annual reports to Congress, beginning in October, 1897, Governor Brady extolled Alaska's bountiful resources and demanded changes in the territory's laws to meet local needs. As early as 1899, he called for statehood as the only remedy for the political and civil disadvantages under which Alaska languished. Brady's administration promoted development of Alaska's natural resources, expansion of trade, and increased settlement. He was re-appointed governor in 1900 and again in 1904, by President Theodore Roosevelt.
In 1905, Brady met H.D. Reynolds of Boston, an adventurer who headed the Reynolds-Alaska Development Company. He invested all his money in Reynolds' enterprises and allowed his name to be advertised as a shareholder and guarantor of the Company. Newspaper articles criticized this apparent conflict of interest, and Secretary of the Interior Ethan A. Hitchcock charged that Brady had acted improperly. This public clamor led Brady to resign as governor in January, 1906. However, Brady vigorously denied that he had been guilty of wrongdoing. Reynolds' various enterprises crashed in 1907, and Brady lost the savings which he had invested. Yet he refused to condemn Reynolds and worked for two years to restore the investments of stockholders who had relied on his advice in supporting Reynolds' schemes.
In 1909, Brady moved to New York to become vice-president of the Corporation Finance Company. He spent most of his remaining years travelling through the United Stages lecturing on Alaska and writing about its history, resources, commercial possibilities, and political needs. He later returned to Sitka, where he died on December 17, 1918.
Scope and Contents
The John G. Brady Papers are arranged in eight series. Series I, Correspondence, is arranged in three sections. Family Correspondence, 1867-1919, includes letters exchanged by John G. Brady, Elizabeth (Patton) Brady, their children, and Brady's foster father, John Green. Many of Brady's letters to Elizabeth from Washington, D.C., New York, and elsewhere describe his efforts to promote Alaska's political and economic interests.
Incoming Correspondence, 1867-1926, consists primarily of personal letters received from friends, Yale classmates, and associates. The most frequent correspondent is Dr. Sheldon Jackson, Brady's missionary colleague and close friend for many years. In addition to personal letters, there is some correspondence received in Brady's official capacity as Governor of Alaska, from 1897 to 1906. A number of letters and petitions recommending Brady's appointment as governor, which had been sent to the President's office for consideration in 1888 and 1889, were turned over to Brady in 1894 when the Department of the Interior closed his applications file. Copies of similar recommendations from 1897 to 1904 are also included. These recommendations are most numerous for 1888 and 1889, when Brady first sought the appointment from President Harrison. Among those writing in his behalf were Frances Willard and other officers of the National Woman's Christian Temperance Union, and representatives of the Presbyterian, Baptist, United Brethren, and Methodist churches. There are also a number of letters of condolence received on the death of John G. Brady in December, 1918. Four letters received by Henry Baldwin and his family, obtained with a group of letters written by Brady to Henry Baldwin, are filed in this section.
Outgoing Correspondence, is arranged in three parts. The first part consists of copies, drafts and a few originals of Brady's letters to friends and associates, dated from 1878 to 1918. The second part consists of pages cut from letter copy books, containing Brady's official correspondence as governor. The bulk of these letters is dated from August, 1901 to April, 1906, with no letters for the period October 1904 to March, 1905, inclusive. The third part of outgoing correspondence consists of bound letter copy books, containing Brady's official correspondence from May, 1899 to April, 1906.
Series II, Diaries, Notebooks and Scrapbooks, is arranged in three parts. Brady's diaries are brief and incomplete, covering the years 1873-80, 1897, 1900 and 1903-07. His notebooks include lecture notes from seminary, 1874-77; copies of letters of Harry D. Reynolds, 1903; copies of Reynolds Alaska Company invoices, 1907; and a guest book, 1899-15. Three of Brady's scrapbooks, covering the years 1885-86 and 1897-1907, contain newsclippings and other materials relating to Brady's career and personal interests.
Series III, Writings, contains autobiographical writings, published and unpublished articles, and research notes. Brady's autobiographical writings relate primarily to his youth, describing his experiences growing up on the streets of New York, living on an Indiana farm, and studying at Yale and Union Theological Seminary. Brady's articles range from brief accounts of incidents in Alaska's history to lengthy descriptions of Alaska's economic resources and political problems. Most of the articles exist in manuscript form, either holograph or typewritten. A large proportion of Brady's research notes on Alaska history and political affairs was compiled from sources at the New York Public Library during the years following his resignation as governor of Alaska.
Series IV, Official, Legal and Financial Papers, includes both official and personal papers. The official papers relate to Alaska governmental affairs for the years 1884 to 1914. The largest group of items in this section is printed Thanksgiving proclamations issued by the governor, from 1892 to 1905. Among the official financial records are payroll receipts, 1891-1899, for individuals serving with the Indian Police. Brady's legal papers include contracts and agreements, legal briefs, property plot maps, documents relating to Alaska business and industry, and a burial permit and an estate distribution decree relating to Brady's death. Financial papers, 1874-1915, consist of Brady's life insurance policies and receipts, and some of his personal bills and receipts.
Series V, Personal and Family Papers, consists of assorted papers of John G. Brady, Elizabeth (Patton) Brady, Mary B. Brady, John G. Brady, Jr., and Cassia Patton. There are six folders of articles and newsclippings about John G. Brady, including a Yale student paper by S.M. Bemiss, "John Green Brady and the Quest for Home Rule in Alaska" (1976). Brady's papers also include certificates, drawings, programs for banquets and meetings which he addressed, and other materials. Elizabeth (Patton) Brady's papers consist of her article on "The Government Community School at Sitka, Alaska," two diaries, and several notebooks. Mary B. Brady's papers consist of two published articles, on which she collaborated and one which she wrote for The Independent. There is a two-page typed diary by John G. Brady, Jr., and one folder of papers on the Alaska Society of History and Ethnology for Cassia Patton. Two notebooks and some unbound notes are unidentified.
Series VI, Printed Material, contains pamphlets, brochures, leaflets, articles, pictures and maps concerning Alaska; scattered issues of several Alaska newspapers; newspaper clippings about Alaska; and several books. The pamphlets, brochures and leaflets were published by United States and Alaska governmental agencies, church and civic organizations, and business firms. The largest groups of materials are United States Government reports and pamphlets, and reports and manuals prepared by the Alaska Department of Education. Although these publications date from 1875 to 1925, most were published after 1918. They were arranged alphabetically by organization. Articles about Alaska, 1885-1926, are arranged chronologically. There are also two folders of maps, 1882-1923, and one folder of printed pictures, 1898-1914.
Scattered issues of newspapers and periodicals include publications from Anchorage, Hyder, Juneau, Ketchikan, Metlakahtla, Rampart, and Sitka, Alaska; and from Boston, New York, St. Louis, San Francisco, Seattle, and Victoria (British Columbia). The earliest issues are the Alaska Herald (San Francisco), 1872-80; the latest issues are The Alaska Daily Empire (Juneau), for 1925 Jan-Nov and 1937 Apr 24. The first part of the newspaper clippings, 1923-24, is arranged by subject. Newspaper clippings not organized under subject headings have been arranged chronologically, from 1878 to 1930. The majority of these newspapers and clippings are dated after John G. Brady's death and were probably collected by Mary B. Brady. The four books in the collection are John G. Brady's Bible and New Testaments (in English and Greek).
Series VII, Photographs, is the largest series in the Brady papers. It includes photographic paper prints, photograph albums, negatives, glass negatives, a printing block, and glass lantern slides. There are approximately 760 photographic prints, including both amateur and professional photographs (see List of Photographers at end of this register), arranged by subject. There are portraits of John G. Brady and his family and photographs of his home and garden at Sitka. Other prominent subjects include buildings, churches, landscapes, mining industry, portraits of groups (native Alaskan and white), portraits of individuals (native Alaskan and white), ships, social activities, totems, and towns. Many of the other photographs depict commercial activities, industry, transportation, social customs, and other aspects of Alaskan life. The photograph albums contain Alaska scenes by Partridge and by Winter and Pond. The negatives include original negatives and negatives prepared from photographs in the Brady collection (see list in box 30, folder 197).
There are approximately 450 glass lantern slides, which Brady used to illustrate his lectures about Alaska. These include most of the subjects found in the photographs. Although there are copies of some of the photographs in the collection, most of the glass slides do not duplicate the paper prints. Important subjects found only in the glass slides include maps, portraits of Laplanders, and the St. Louis World's Fair.
Series VIII, City of Sitka Records, consists of papers of the mayor, City Council, and other offices of the City of Sitka, from 1867 to 1873. These papers include correspondence received by the mayor and by the City Council, minutes of City Council meetings, resolutions and ordinances passed by City Council, court records, election records, and financial records, including tax lists, bills and receipts.
Sitka (Alaska); Alaska Herald; The Alaska Daily Empire; Indians of North America -- Alaska -- Pictorial works; Missions -- Alaska; Alaska -- History -- 1867-1959; Alaska -- Politics and government -- 1867-1959; Sitka (Alaska) -- Pictorial works; Diaries -- United States; Lantern slides -- United States; Missionaries -- Alaska; Public officers -- Alaska; Baldwin, Henry; Brady, John G., Mrs.; Brady, John Green, 1847-1918; Ingersoll, T. W. (Truman Ward), 1862-1922; Jackson, Sheldon, 1834-1909; Reynolds, Harry D.; Taber, I. W. (Isaiah West), 1830-1912; Alaska. Department of Education; Reynolds Alaska Company
- Correspondence, 1867-1926; Series I; 2.5' (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized in three sections. Family Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Incoming Correspondence is also arranged chronologically, with separate categories of letters at the end: letters, recommending Brady's appointment as governor, letters received on the death of John G. Brady, and letters of Henry Baldwin and family, each arranged chronologically. Outgoing Correspondence is organized in three parts, each arranged chronologically: loose letters and drafts, letter copy books (unbound), and letter copy books (bound).
  - Family correspondence, 1867-86 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family correspondence, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Family correspondence, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family correspondence, 1897 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family correspondence, 1897 Apr-Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family correspondence, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family correspondence, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence, 1900 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family correspondence, 1900 May-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family correspondence, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family correspondence, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Family correspondence, 1903 Jan-Aug (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Family correspondence, 1903 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family correspondence, 1904 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Family correspondence, 1904 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Family correspondence, 1904 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Family correspondence, 1904 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Family correspondence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Family correspondence, 1906-07 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Family correspondence, 1917-19 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1867-69 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1870-71 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1872-74 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1875-76 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1877-79 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1880-81 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1882-86 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1887-96 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1897 Jan-Aug (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1897 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1899 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1899 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1900 Jan-Jul (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1900 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1902 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1902 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1905-07 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1914-17 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1918-26 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Letters recommending Brady's appointment as Governor, 1888-89 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Letters recommending Brady's appointment as Governor, 1894-1904 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Letters received on the death of John G. Brady, 1918 Dec (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Letters received on the death of John G. Brady, 1919 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Letters of Henry Baldwin and family, 1879, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1878-83 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1884-86 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1887-89 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1891-96 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1897-98 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1899-1901 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1902-03 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1904-06 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1910-14 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1916-18 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1890-99 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1901 Aug-Sep (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1901 Oct-Dec (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1902 Jan-Mar (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1902 Apr-May (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1902 Jun (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1902 Jul-Sep (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1902 Oct (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1902 Nov-Dec (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Jan (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Feb (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Mar-Apr (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 May (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Jun-Aug (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Sep 1-5 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Sep 6-30 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Oct 1-14 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Oct 15-31 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Nov (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Dec 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1903 Dec 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1904 Jan-Feb (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1904 Mar (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1904 Apr-Sep (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Apr (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 May (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Jun (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Jul (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Aug (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Sep (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Oct (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Nov (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1905 Dec (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Letter copy book (unbound), 1906 Jan-Apr (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1901 Feb-1903 Mar (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1903 Mar-1905 Apr (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1904 Jan-Mar (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1904 Mar-1905 Apr (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1905 Mar-Jun (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1905 Apr-Jul (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1905 Aug-1906 Apr (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Letter copy book (bound), 1899 May-1900 Oct (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 101)
- Diaries, Notebooks and Scrapbooks, 1873-1915; Series II; 1.5' (3 boxes)
  This series is organized by form of material--diary, notebook, guest book, scrapbook--each of which is arranged chronologically.
  - Diary, 1873-74 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1875, 1878 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1875-80 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1903-07 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Notebooks: lecture notes, 1874-76 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Notes: seminary, 1874-77 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks, 1887-91, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Notebooks: letters of Harry D. Reynolds, 1903 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Notebooks, 1906-07 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Notebook: copies of invoices, Reynolds Alaska Company, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Notebook: inventory of Brady books, 1912
  - Notebooks (with enclosures), 1916, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Guest book, 1899-1915 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1885-86 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook, 1897-1903 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook, 1899-1907 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Writings, 1896-1917; Series III; 1' (3 boxes)
  This series is organized in three subseries. Autobiographical writings are arranged chronologically. Brady's published and unpublished articles and speeches are arranged chronologically; following the dated articles are undated manuscripts, which are arranged alphabetically. Research notes identified by subject are arranged alphabetically by heading, with unidentified notebooks at the end.
  - AUTOBIOGRAPHY
    - "The Problem of Myself, or, the Story of a New York Boy," AMs, 1916 Jul (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "The Zigzags of a New York Boy," TMs, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "John Green Brady," AMs, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - ARTICLES AND SPEECHES
    - "Alaska," AMs, 1896 Sep (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "Alaska," in The Chautauquan, 1896 Sep (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - "Alaska," in The Chautauquan (duplicate), 1896 Sep (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Witchcraft in Alaska," in The Independent, 1898 Dec 29 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - "Alaska: Its Resources and Needs," in The Independent, 1900 Jan 18 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - "Speech Delivered at Juneau, July 4, 1903," AMs, TMs, 1903 Jul (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - "Mining," AMs, c. 1903 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - "Report on Alaska, 1905," TMs (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Reynolds Alaska Development Company: statements to stockholders, AMs, 1907, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Letter to the Editor of the Boston Transcript, TMs, 1908 May 15 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "The Legal Rights of the Alaskan Natives Undetermined by Congress," AMs, TMs, c. 1908 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - "Tomfoolery with Alaska" (version 1), AMs, TMs, c. 1910 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - "The Mal-Administration of Affairs in Alaska," in Commerce and Industries Magazine, 1911 Sep (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - "A Condition of Mind," AMs, TMs, 1911 Oct (Box 10, Folder 17)